<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elliot Herriman</title>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <description>A website with blog posts and pages</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 19:45:13 -0500</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>'Disobedience' Review</title>
        <link>/Disobedience-2018/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Disobedience-2018/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt; isn’t the film I wanted it to be, but that doesn’t make it any less important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you watched a movie blind? Not just unspoiled ― I’m talking no trailers, no synopsis, not even a premise. I’ve heard many swear by it, but having made it forty five minutes into &lt;em&gt;Dr. Strangelove&lt;/em&gt; before realising it was a comedy, I’ve since decided the practice isn’t quite for me. The first ten or twenty minutes of any movie is designed to set up the characters and plot, but without the context that IMDb or a friendly neighborhood film critic might give you, you’re often left disoriented, forced to figure out exactly where the film’s focus lies. It can be fun at times, but it’s also far too easy to get the wrong idea of where a film is headed, and end up disappointed over that disconnect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine sitting down to watch &lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt;, a film you’re so sure will tell the forbidden love of two women raised in a strict religious community, and getting… something else entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt;’s marketing heavily styled it as a queer romantic drama with a religious coat of paint, and it often is. But watching it through this lens, something started to feel off to me around the one hour mark. In truth, even though it dabbles in this subject, that just isn’t the kind of film &lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt; wants to be. Rather, it chases themes of faith and freedom, using sexuality as a lens through which to explore them. There’s overlap between these two approaches, admittedly, but they’re meaningfully distinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet not meaningfully distinguished, if audience reactions are anything to go by. Though &lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt; has been critically acclaimed, discussions have seemed largely underlined by a dissatisfaction over the film’s ultimate direction, a lot of which I’d guess comes from a disconnect between audience expectation and the film as presented. Through a lens of sexuality and sexual liberation, the film’s direction feels somewhat unsatisfying, yes, but that’s largely because that’s not what this film is about. This isn’t a film about the two women and their relationship. It’s about each woman’s relationship with herself, her faith, and the culture that raised her. It’s about both women finding the freedom to choose what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is more than okay. It’s good, even. &lt;em&gt;Disobedience&lt;/em&gt; is a fantastic film for what it is ― but I think its greatest obstacle will be convincing its audience of what it isn’t. It might be a little less accessible than your standard independent drama, but it’s well worth the trouble, just so long as you understand that this isn’t quite the film you’re hoping for. Which I can’t fault it for, really. This isn’t a matter of it missing my expectations, so much as it is my expectations missing it. I have no doubt I’d enjoy it much more on a second viewing, because it is a damn good movie. It’s just also not the one that I, and many others, wanted it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published by The Pelican on June 30, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>'Kodachrome' Review</title>
        <link>/Kodachrome-2018-Review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Kodachrome-2018-Review/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey, directors of the future, can you maybe romanticise some hobbies that &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; bankrupt me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on an article in the New York Times by A.G. Sulzberger, Kodachrome is a movie about death, family, and analog film — and the surprising overlap you can find between the three. When Matt (Jason Sudeikis) is contacted by his estranged father Ben (Ed Harris), who only has months to live, the two set out on a road trip to the last remaining Kodachrome film development lab before it closes its doors forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed Harris is fantastic, as per usual, and Jason Sudeikis — who was absolutely electrifying in last year’s Colossal — hits it out of the park again with a role that’s indistinguishable from your archetypal snarky white guy in a dramedy, right up until he blindsides you with something powerful and complex. Special mention should go to Elizabeth Olson, too. This might not be her movie, but she’s an absolute powerhouse here, bringing her best performance since Wind River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen the word predictable thrown around in discussions of this movie online. For what it’s worth, I don’t think predictability is ever inherently bad, nor is it something you should ever let dissuade you from enjoying a film — but if it’s really the sort of thing you can’t stand, then rest assured: Kodachrome hits the beats you’d expect, yes, but it hits them well. I reviewed Cargo last week, a film that’s remarkably upfront with how it’s going to end, and I think Kodachrome works in a similar way at times — but in neither case does this ever work to the film’s detriment. Even though you might expect a moment to come, it never seems to be exactly when or how you predicted. Which is clever, but even though it works well here, I don’t think this subversion of expectation is ever necessary to make a predictable movie good — and it’s certainly not the only thing that makes Kodachrome work. For me to call the movie’s final scene beat for beat before the halfway point and still cry as much as I did represents some seriously smart filmmaking, and screenwriter Jonathan Tropper deserves credit for just how well Kodachrome works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels apt that Kodachrome has so much to say about analog photography, records, and other mediums of the past — while it may have an international run in cinemas, the North American distribution rights for Kodachrome were bought up by Netflix. I’ve never quite understood the desire to preserve analog film and photography as a medium, but sitting in a darkened theatre as the credits rolled, feeling vaguely sour that so many would first see this movie on their laptop, something clicked for me. This has never been about how vivid film can look, or how warm records might sound. It’s about what these mediums mean to individuals, and what losing them might represent. As much as I enjoyed it, I know that Kodachrome is going to end up being the sort of movie you’ll find on Netflix in a year or two, and genuinely enjoy, but never seek out in cinemas — and I think that’s a damn shame. Wait a few months if you must, but I’d urge you to seek out showtimes. There’s so much to love here, and it’s only on the big screen once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published by The Pelican on June 5, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>'Cargo' Review</title>
        <link>/Cargo-2018-Review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Cargo-2018-Review/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A surprisingly fresh approach to an otherwise shambling genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems appropriate that as a genre, zombies have simply refused to die. Horror trends being run into the ground is nothing new — remember found footage? — but the fact that we’re all still willing to tolerate the zombies in our films is perhaps a testament to just how the genre can be at its best. Case in point, Cargo, a film with enough creativity and innovation to fuel another season’s worth of collective interest in The Walking Dead. Directed by Australians Yolanda Ramke and Ben Howling and based on their critically acclaimed short film of the same name, Cargo is a fascinating example of just how far the definition of horror as a genre can be stretched. It’s also good, and will no doubt serve as a point of inspiration to Australian filmmakers for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Cargo, civilisation has collapsed, and the dead are walking. With no hope of rescue in sight, Andy and Kay Caine (Martin Freeman and Susie Porter) have holed up with their infant daughter in an abandoned houseboat — until dwindling supplies force them to venture out into the deadly Australian outback in the hopes of finding safe haven. Interspersed through these early scenes is Thoomi (Simone Landers), an indigenous girl who soon sees her path intertwined with that of Andy’s family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cargo feels noteworthy for its extensive depiction of indigenous cultures and spirituality, topics that are rarely depicted by feature films. There were a small number of moments that could arguably have been handled better, but the movie’s overall representation of these subjects is surprisingly well done, and Cargo largely avoids the pitfalls that a movie like this might otherwise have stumbled into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of Cargo’s success as a short film undoubtedly came from its original approach to zombies at the time. As a feature, Cargo aims for something similarly fresh, by offering a horror movie that frequently shirks the chance to scare. There’s incredible tension to be found in its premise, of course, but Cargo is more interested in telling a compelling story than it is scaring its audience. Zombies aren’t used as an explicit source of fear from scene to scene, so much as they are an ever circling threat that feeds into a feeling of inevitability and hopelessness. Likewise, there’s no shortage of unease, yet only a few genuine scares — and the denouement is remarkably quiet and character driven for a film that bills itself as horror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet it works. The desperation and despair radiating from Freeman’s character is palpable, and it’s perhaps thanks to this — alongside a more subdued approach to the genre and an understated finale — that Cargo hits its audience like a fist to the gut. It’s almost a shame Cargo shies away from frequent scares, because the few scenes that don’t are remarkably effective — but Ramke and Howling’s subtle, relentless direction feels integral to what makes this film tick, building Cargo’s characters and conflicts in a way that jump scares and rampant terror could only have distracted from. Scary or not, this is horror that’s well worth your time. Cargo is a genuinely good movie, a tremendous debut, and one of the best Australian films I’ve seen in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published by The Pelican on May 17, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charlie Brooker's Baby Boomer Fever Dream</title>
        <link>/what-if-charlie-brooker-but-too-much/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/what-if-charlie-brooker-but-too-much/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We need to have a serious talk about the role of technology in our society. Just… not like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not much of a stretch to say that science fiction as a genre of movies largely tends towards social commentary. Sure, there have always been works like &lt;em&gt;Transformers&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;, but as a whole, sci–fi cinema has an established pattern of discussing otherwise highly charged cultural anxieties in a candid, hypothetical fashion. Science fiction films of the fifties and sixties explored common anxieties around nuclear power and war, with monsters like &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The 50 Foot Woman&lt;/em&gt; created from experiments gone wrong. The seventies and eighties brought films like &lt;em&gt;Soylent Green&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt;, depicting a society threatened by the very advancements it had itself created, but by the time the nineties rolled around, these had evolved into narratives on technology with classics like &lt;em&gt;Terminator 2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;. Oddly enough, most sci–fi films released in the wake of September 11 actually subverted this pattern by avoiding invasion as a subject matter entirely — the only notable exception that comes to mind is &lt;em&gt;Cloverfield&lt;/em&gt;, and that wasn’t released until 2008. Still, there was an noticeable rise in the depiction of surveillance states, alongside a slew of disaster movies like &lt;em&gt;The Day After Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; that were rather unsubtly inspired by a growing debate on climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all this in mind, I’d like to draw your attention to &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re unfamiliar, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is an anthology television series that sits in something of a grey area between science–fiction and horror. The brain child of Charlie Brooker — a name I only mention now so I can chew him out later — &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; first aired on the BBC for two seasons before moving to Netflix for its third and fourth. Like any other science fiction anthology, comparisons have inevitably been drawn between &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; and the genre–defining &lt;em&gt;Twilight Zone&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; has made a name for itself by choosing to exclusively depict stories about technology. According to Netflix’s press kit, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; “taps into our collective unease with the modern world”, literally holding up our phones and computer screens as “a &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; reflecting our 21st Century existence back at us”. The show is well produced on a technical level, and between a jet black tone and an abundance of twist endings, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; has proven remarkably popular. The problem as I see it, however, is that while &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; may claim to show us a candid portrait of modern society, it does so by merely depicting elements of our cultural anxieties in place of offering actual insight. Science fiction might not be under any sort of obligation to offer meaningful social commentary, but &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is seemingly so determined to criticise technology that it fails to connect with the very social anxieties that inspired it in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tie all this together, yes, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; certainly seems like a reaction to the rapid growth of the internet over this past decade. At this point, the idea that phones and social media are causing us to grow isolated from one another is more or less synonymous with the phrase “back in my day,” but that doesn’t necessarily mean &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;’s obvious cynicism is without merit. The trouble is, this cynicism seems to be the only message that &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is interested in offering. Although most episodes do seem to start with an open mind and an interesting premise, the conflict is consistently driven by the presence of technology, and this seriously limits the direction that any given story can take. On top of this, rather than holding characters responsible for their actions, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; has a habit of implying that technology is at fault, and this is no more obvious than in an episode like &lt;em&gt;The Entire History of You&lt;/em&gt;. The episode is centered around an implant that allows characters to replay and project their memories, and although it’s unsurprising that a story like this would choose to focus on jealousy and distrust as themes, the way in which the narrative seemingly pins responsibility for this jealousy on the technology itself feels strange. Instead of encouraging its audience to explore the ways that we individually and collectively deal with emotions like jealousy, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; chooses to absolve its characters of any responsibility by telling us that actually, it was technology’s fault the whole time. That’s not to say characters aren’t punished, but it feels more often than not that they’re being punished for their use of technology instead of their actions, with &lt;em&gt;Playtest&lt;/em&gt; being a downright bizarre example of this. None of this is necessarily a bad thing, but &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;’s compulsive demonization of technology has a habit of drowning out any message or insight it might otherwise have had to offer — and nowhere is this more obvious than in the masterpiece that is &lt;em&gt;San Junipero&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easily the best that the the series has to offer, &lt;em&gt;San Junipero&lt;/em&gt; exists in remarkable contrast to the rest of the series. It’s a stubborn subversion of everything &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is otherwise known for: there’s no moralising on the dangers of the internet, no dark twist ending that serves to upend the moral of the story. It’s considerably more optimistic than the rest of the series, too, but I honestly think the reason this episode works so well is that it only uses technology as a way of contextualising the narrative, rather than presenting technology as the driving source of conflict. Brooker’s conservative sentiments take a back seat, meaning that by the time the credits roll, the audience is left with something meaningful — not answers, for once, but concepts and themes they’re forced to grapple with, and it works in a way no other episode of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; can hope to match. To me, that might actually be the most frustrating part. If &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; just got out of its own way and stopped trying to hand us the answers it’s looking for, there’s no doubt in my mind we’d see more episodes like &lt;em&gt;San Junipero&lt;/em&gt;. As it is, we just have a handful of stories that come &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; to connecting us with our fears. I mean, what if &lt;em&gt;Arkangel&lt;/em&gt; had focused on the dilemmas parents undoubtedly face today around raising children in an age of social media? What if &lt;em&gt;Hated in the Nation&lt;/em&gt; had explored the way people handle criticism and consequence over their actions online, instead of literally equating call–out culture with murder? What if &lt;em&gt;Hang the DJ&lt;/em&gt; had explored the casual dating scene ushered in by apps like Tinder, examining what it’s like to be in a relationship that you don’t expect to last? These are issues that many of us have grappled with, but &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; comes so close to helping us confront them, but every time it seems more interested in criticising technology than it is connecting with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this ends up meaning is that rather than offering us the chance to reflect candidly on our anxieties, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; handles catharsis in a way much more reminiscent of campy horror. Characters indulge in things that we’re all at least a little anxious might be wrong, like sex, drugs, or social media, and then we as an audience feel some sort of relief or distress when we finally see their comeuppance — which isn’t bad, so much as it is deceptive. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; claims to hold up a reflection of our modern society, and what you get certainly &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like cutting introspection, but it’s not even close. It’s just shock tactics, played on repeat, and the worst part is that &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;’s approach is only going to further entrench us in our opinions. It doesn’t prompt or enable discussion, it doesn’t try to find a middle ground or bridge divides, it just wants to scare you into deleting your Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which, given recent events concerning Facebook and targeted advertising and the extensive profiles that companies have built on us, given the discomfort around social media that I can visibly see growing around me, it feels important now more than ever to actually have these serious conversations — to actually reflect on the role of technology and the internet in our society. Yet somehow, despite all of this, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; seems to be the only current major science fiction property that’s plugged into these anxieties. Other sci–fi works in recent years like &lt;em&gt;Westworld&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ex Machina&lt;/em&gt; have touched on the subject, but instead largely focus the artificial intelligence, meaning that even if they do have insight to offer, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is still what we joke about when Google does something sinister. We don’t need good sci–fi to deal with issues as a society, of course, but we’ve come as a culture to connect with others through our entertainment, and the fact that &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; has become the de–facto frame of reference for discussions on the role of technology in our society has made it that much harder to talk about these issues in a meaningful way. There’s plenty to be said for &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; as entertainment, but as the loudest voice on these issues right now, we deserve something that aims for more than the only story &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; seems interested in telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published in the May 2018 issue of The Pelican, under the title &lt;em&gt;‘Black Mirror’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument that Black Mirror feels closer to horror than science fiction was first brought to my attention by Film Crit Hulk in his article &lt;a href=&quot;https://birthmoviesdeath.com/2016/10/27/black-mirror-is-kinda-bullshit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror Is Kinda Bullshit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
